Ashtami Puja, Eighth day of Navaratri,
Meudon, Paris (France), 30 September 1984.
Today is the eighth day of Navaratri,
Loudly.
and it is great day for Sahaja Yogis
because it is the
most important time, period.
That is, the seventh centre,
we have crossed, and we are on the eighth centre.
We need not think about the
Goddess what She did on the eighth day,
we have to think today what
we have to do within ourselves.
After crossing the seventh day,
after crossing the seventh chakra
that is the real ascent in your spiritual ascent.
What are we to do on the eighth one?
It’s so Sahaja that today should be the Ashtami,
because that is the day the
Goddess killed so may evil doers,
and devils and Rakshasas.
She did it on Her own, alone.
Now these evil forces are manifesting in human beings.
They have spread out.
They are within us.
So we all have to fight
those forces within us.
The war is within ourselves,
is not without.
First when you ascend the seventh chakra
and you are on the eighth step,
you have to remember first you have
to fight those forces within ourselves.
You are all very intelligent people;
bit too intelligent sometimes.
So whatever I say you may twist it,
and may try to use it in your own intelligence.
But it is not in your well-being.
It is not for your ‘hita’, for your good.
You want to use it because
you think you are intelligent,
or maybe that you don't
know you are using it that way.
And that is what one has to know
that these forces are acting within us.
They act through our intelligence,
they act through our emotions,
and they act through our physical being.
So we have to be very careful.
When you ascend into Sahaja Yoga,
we have to be very careful with our intelligence,
because intelligence has capacity to cheat itself.
And it will cheat us, nobody else.
It is against us, our own
wealth, against our own powers.
So we have to be alert
and see for ourselves.
So as soon as you enter onto the eighth
step you should start seeing at yourself.
Now, for example,
for example, when I say the
mantra is “I am my own Guru”,
immediately the intelligence comes
forward to render its services-freely.
“Oh! I am my own Guru,
why should I listen to anyone?
Why should I listen to any leader? Why
should I listen to anybody who is elder,
who understands Sahaja Yoga better?
I am my own Guru!”
The other way it is.
Straightforward thing is that: I am
My own Guru, I have to correct myself.
I have to use this instrument
of light to correct myself.
Now the intelligence cheats again:
“Mother said that if your feel
vibrations, then it’s alright;
and I am feeling the vibrations, I am alright”.
Again cheating.
You are cheating yourself!
Why? What is the reason?
The reason is very interesting.
I’ve seen that ordinary human beings
– in the West specially
– are very much against themselves.
Like, I’ll give you an example:
You tell somebody that if
you have to go to the station,
take this road and you’ll
go straight to the station.
But immediately he’ll say,
“But the problem is,
that how can I go straight?
My back is towards the station.
If I walk straight I’ll go in
the opposite direction of the station”.
Such stupid things! But they say it, all the time.
Now if you tell them that you can sell your
car better if you go to Germany, for example;
but they say, “There’s a problem,
maybe the Germans may start their war again.
Maybe there is Hitler waiting for me, to kill me”.
Any fantastic problem, that you can’t never
think of, can come out of this modern brain.
And you are amazed how this
man is against himself all the time!
The whole built-up is like that because before
realisation you are absolutely disintegrated.
Your heart is against your brain,
and your brain is against your liver.
This is the reason they have three types of wives;
one is a love affair,
one is a physical life and one is a wife.
They are so disintegrated that every
cell can have a wife or can have a husband.
The nose will want something,
the eyes will want another thing,
and the hands will do something else
and tongue will say something else.
When I met the western people,
I had to consult many
dictionaries to understand them.
Could not understand why
they behave in such a funny manner.
They are all the time against themselves.
So after realisation this
habit becomes even subtler.
So now they use Sahaja Yoga
to act against Sahaja Yoga itself.
Sahaja is simple, is straightforward.
They don’t want to have it in that way.
They must always do it in such
a way that it is absolutely Asahaja.
There was a fellow in my house
who was suffering from left side problems.
So I told him that you have to light a lamp
and then take out all your badhas every night.
And we had a big drum of oil in the house.
He did not eat any food, he did not sleep.
He burnt all that oil in one week’s time.
He burnt all the...
He made all the blankets black,
all the walls black, and burnt all the curtains!
When I came back after eight days,
I said what have you been doing?
–And he looked like a real bhoot!
He said “I was driving out the bhoots.”
I said now this is the limit!
So he said, “Mother you told me”,
I said, “Thank god you did not take
beacon light to burn the whole house!”
So I have to be very careful when I talk with you.
Whenever I tell you one thing, I tell you that
other side of it also immediately,
because I don’t want if I tell you this side,
you go to the other side, to the other extreme.
So all this kind of this crazy
madness, stupidness I’ve seen.
And today when I’m going to talk to you about
discipline, I must tell you “Discipline has to be Sahaja”.
Now what does that mean?
That is first of all “face yourself”.
What I find, that the western mind,
because of its ego, cannot discipline itself.
If you tell them you have to discipline
they think I’m creating a military out of you.
In a way it ‘is’ a fight.
It is a fight with yourself.
But how will you fight if you have no discipline?
Now if I say, you have to get
up in the morning, take your bath,
and sit down for meditation;
in a Sahaja way you have to tell yourself plainly,
“Come along, now you have
to get up tomorrow morning”.
In a Sahaja way; the way
you turn your wheels in your car.
So what you do is to, I think,
the whole night you don’t sleep.
Maybe this could be one extreme, is not to sleep.
And get up at 2 o'clock,
disturb the whole house-hold,
fill your tub, and fill
the whole house with water!
And sit down in the
water, and you get cold and sick.
It is absurd!
Why? Because you want to show-off.
Or maybe you want to hurt yourself.
Both things are wrong.
Whatever has to be done has to
be done in the most pleasurable way.
Either you will not wash the dirt, or you
will wash it such that all the cloth will be torn.
But today as I see the people
—of France, specially,
the French Sahaja Yogis,
I think the discipline is lacking.
I’m quite surprised at it.
The first thing it hits at is that
you cannot manage within a limited amount,
I mean money-wise. It hits you at the money point.
Like in the room there’s light,
nobody will see that it is put off; there’s also
a switch to be put off;–is a practical thing.
I mean one must know.
And the light bill is going
for nothing at all, going up.
Is an irresponsibility, complete irresponsibility.
That it is the money that will be spent,
is just a waste; and for us it is
important to live within sensible means.
First I’ll be dealing with gross discipline.
Now what happens, that if
somebody says why the light is on,
immediately they become very
abstract, they say “We are the light”.
Then you should not have lights at all,
there’s no need to have any light!
Save all the electricity, all the light.
You are the Sun, so you need not have any heating!
That is the way things are funny.
One must understand that on the gross points
we have to disciplined first, and foremost….
We are living in ‘France, not on Himalayas.
So when you live in France, we have
to correct ourselves living in France'.
Now the second gross point is that
there are many who are not working at all.
Is a hippy style life.
Or they work for two days or three days,
and the rest of the time what do they do?
They say we meditate.
Means what? They sleep and snore, that’s all.
You don’t need 24 hours to meditate.
You ‘must’ have jobs, all of you!
Regular jobs.
So many ladies I’m told don’t take jobs once
they marry. They say “let the husband do job”.
It’s very wrong.
If you have the child,
it’s all right, for the time being.
You all must work every day.
There is no day for when we can rest, really.
God created this world in six
days and seventh day He rested.
But the eighth day what did He do?
He started giving realisation; relentlessly.
Working hard.
Could you believe at this age of mine,
within last 2 months how much I have travelled?
Every night sleeping at about 2
o'clock, getting up about 5 o'clock:
I went to America,
came back from there, then throughout England,
the whole month I was travelling
—from north to south, east to west.
Next month out to Switzerland, to Zermatt.
Then to Austria, Munich.
Then back to London.
Then to Italy,
back to London.
Had a Puja there. Again back to France.
Again back to London.
I’ve to change my house,
pack up all the things,
go back to India,
go to Hong Kong, go to China, come back.
Then look after your Ashrams in India.
Six days. Again, come back.
And then to America…
That’s the thing your Mother is doing at this age.
Last night we slept at 3:30.
But then they told us that it’s one hour earlier.
So, we said all right one
hour earlier. So, we slept at 2:30!
But you have to make your body like that,
you see that it should
stand all kinds of discomforts.
You know in Sahaja Yoga
unemployment is not allowed;
to take this money from
the Government is not allowed.
You’ll be surprised; in England we
have maximum unemployment in the whole world,
but there is no Sahaja Yogi is unemployed.
Now you all must earn
sufficiently to pay for your stay.
Nobody should be parasite.
Now the young people who are not educated,
who have no other job
but that of a...
What do you call it? Labour class
or we call it as the garbage cleaners,
must take some sort of
specialisation, to some kind of a mastery,
otherwise people think that
Sahaja Yoga is a group of beggars.
Beggars and unemployed and miserable people.
But you see, when you become your own Guru.
You think that all the Gurus don’t work;
you see their disciples
have to look after them.
The Guru sits down nicely in one
place, and the disciples you see look after.
But not your Guru!
Your Guru has to work very hard.
So you have to be in the
same pattern as your Guru is.
And to hear that “nobody listens, you
tell them anything they don’t do any work,
they are lazy-lumps” is very sad.
Some people sometimes say that
these are the set of lotus-eaters
or some sort of a set of beggars or lepers
who are suffering from horrible diseases.
Then I feel extremely insulted, you know.
You are My children.
How people are going to have respect for you,
or for Me, if you have no discipline?
For French I should say, they
should take to “Mauna” means silence.
Once they take out their lips,
they go on like this, like a bird, I’ve seen:
all the time chuck chuck chuck chuck chuck...
You should exchange with English, who never talk,
they need a bump on the head to
talk.
You ask them ten questions, and they
would not say anything, they’ll just stare.
These two extremes I can’t understand.
Now it’s better to keep quiet,
or it is difficult for us to say
something pleasant to others.
So the first mantra should be, “Mother, teach
us some nice things that we can say to others”.
“What should I say nice tomorrow,
or today, let’s say, today when I get up.
What should I say?
What would give peace to others?”
But not so.
It’s not never the mind
thinks, now, in the morning
I’m going to start with a big spoon,
hitting everyone, “Get up, get up, get up”.
The discipline has to come from ‘within’ yourself.
Nobody has to tell you.
And when somebody tells, you feel hurt.
So I don’t know how to tell
all this that it goes into your heart
and doesn’t remain somewhere in the air.
The discipline of within is
like fragrance of [a] flower.
It gives you complete freedom,
and it gives freedom to others.
See, I would say, I have
certain bad habits or good habits.
Supposing I have a key,
which is very gross thing: key.
At any cost I will not put it here
and there. I’ll put it at the right place.
So, if the key is missing I’m sure it is
lost by somebody else and not by me.
I’m sure about it, because I know myself
very well, I cannot put it anywhere else.
Are you sure about yourself?
Because you are not disciplined, you are not sure.
Like I asked somebody “How are you”?
The person says...
French,
French style.
And Italian style...
they go inside.
Confused, I’m confused – English.
Now, what is that?
Are you realised or not?
They’ve been very kind,
you see, to Me, they think.
Now the time is so short
and you are going like this...
What should I feel?
So today is the day when
your Mother took out
the sword to kill all the enemies,
and you have to kill the greatest enemy
within you, indiscipline and irresponsibility.
Funny ideas people use to justify
their stupidity and their indiscipline.
I know of a Sahaja Yogi who would
never take a bath, for a year at least!
And he was reported to Me.
And when I asked him, why
don’t you take bath, he said, “I’m detached”.
So I said you go and live
in Himalayas with this detachment,
you see others are feeling attached.
Other are feeling impossible to live with you.
You have to be kind to others.
You have to neat and clean, is a very
simple thing that I have to tell you now.
All these are the signs of inner cleanliness.
So we come to the subtler side.
And the subtler side of Sahaja
Yoga is extremely simple.
Is compassion.
Is forgiveness.
Is love.
But the greatest of all, is the service to God.
We are doing the work of God.
How can we be tired?
How can we be unhappy?
The dynamic is flowing through us,
that compassion is so fulfilling,
that love is so beautifying
that how can we not do it?
We should run to do it.
But we have to know that this love
has a “tremendous” urge within itself.
For example, if you
love someone, if you have a child,
how, how worried you are about that child,
how much you work for that child.
If the compassion is manifested,
you will see the whole
world is created out of that.
God has created this universe, this world
and you people out of this compassion
only, just His compassion.
Somebody asked Me one day,
“why did you take this headache upon Himself?”
This headache is so nice,
is such a beautiful burden,
because there are so many possibilities.
So one has to be optimistic.
But you will realise when you are optimistic,
you give lectures to others
but not to yourself that,
“ ‘I’ have to optimistic of improving myself.
Optimistic in my own love.
It’s so rewarding,
it’s so joy giving”.
Such people come up very fast,
their Kundalini rises very fast.
They become beautiful people.
They do constructive work in Sahaja Yoga.
They do not create rifts and groups.
They don’t use Sahaja
Yoga for fulfilling their ego
but they use Sahaja Yoga for
fulfilling their spiritual ascent.
It depends on how you want to use it.
So today on this day of Ashtami,
which is a very powerful day,
you assume that power within yourself that I can
fight all these horrible diseases within myself.
And for others I will have compassion and love.
I will have not others!
This is the point we miss always. They think
“Mother is giving lectures to others not to me.”
And that compassion will bring
forth the beauty of Sahaja Yoga.
There are certain divine laws.
And you cannot cross them.
If you cross them, I cannot help you at all.
Now if you say, “That I put chillies
in my eyes, they should not burn”,
I can’t help you.
Whatever are divine laws you must follow them.
Like in France, if you drive on the
right side, you will jump in the river.
Gauche is left?
Translator: Left.
Shri Mataji: No, right.
Translator: We drive right.
Shri Mataji: You drive right.
Translator: The English drive left.
Shri Mataji: So I was saying
that if you in France, drive right
then you are in trouble.
Translator: We do drive right.
Shri Mataji: You drive right?
Translator: Yes
Shri Mataji: Oh I see. So here if you drive left,
I will be in trouble, I must say!
Because I don’t understand human laws so well!
Like in England different law,
in France another law, in America another law.
Funny people.
But in God’s realm, everywhere the same law.
Whether you are in France,
or England, or India, same law.
Whether on this earth or on the moon,
or on the Jupiter, same laws.
Whether in human beings,
animals or nature, same laws.
But you know the law.
You are the drivers,
so you have to be careful.
If the driver does not know
driving laws, God save passengers.
So, one must know that
these are the laws of the divine,
that we have to live with self-respect,
that we have to be chaste,
that we have to have dignity,
that we cannot steal things and steal money
and [be] parasites.
That we cannot kill others and we cannot beat
others and say harsh things, they are just the same.
And that we have respect,
the respect for all that is sublime.
Respect for all the saints that are Sahaja Yogis.
And the respect for the leaders
who represent your Mother.
With all this, we are very different people.
We are different race.
We are virtuous, we are righteous
and we are proud to be that way.
We are sure of everything.
We know about everything.
And we are personified
or we are personification
of compassion, of love of God.
That’s what we are.
We are not ordinary people.
I asked a child, “Who is our friend?”
She said, “Only one”.
I said, “Why?”
“Because she is a Sahaja Yogini,
the rest are all ordinary people”.
What about the teacher?
“Very ordinary”.
And what about your Headmistress?
“She is absolutely ordinary!”
Then I showed her the
photograph of the Prime Minister.
She looked at it and she was quite surprised.
She said, “this one is even more
ordinary than my headmistress”.
She said with great, you see, disgust,
“Mother why do you keep
such photographs with you?”
That’s what we are.
The children understand more than us, is it?
Because our brain is against us perhaps,
sometimes; over developed brain.
So, yesterday I saw many people
having Ekadasha, I was surprised.
So, I told them just say,
“Mother, you be in my head”.
Because I have no intelligence.
I’m too simple.
You should all become simple like Me.
Absolutely simple person.
That’s very effective!
Now I must say, yesterday
I was a little surprised that
there were two ladies that
were very emotionally disturbed.
And rather dangerously disturbed.
I would like to meet them after the program.
Now I think I have covered most of the points.
But if you have any question,
you can ask Me today.
Sahaja Yogi: Shri Mother,
quite sometimes the chakras,
the same chakras, we feel them
more on legs than on the fingers?
Shri Mataji: The integration is not there,
that’s why. You have to attend collectively.
You have to be more collective;
the body has to be collective.
The thing is that if you
are not a collective person
then sometimes you’ll feel them on the legs,
sometimes on the heart, sometimes in the head.
That’s not a good thing. You should
try to be more collective, you should
meet more people, take more interest.
You see, the body of yours won’t work out
efficiently unless and until you use it.
Because individually, you see,
individually if you work out,
it will not develop collectively,
because where are you using it?
You are correcting yourself to give it to others.
And if you don’t give it, if you do
not work it out in a collective way,
there is no circulation.
For example, there’s a, say, a fruit is there
and you take it out of a tree,
and you mature it.
Outside.
But it will decay very soon.
But if it is connected with the tree,
it will mature by itself
giving a proper identity to itself
and to the tree.
And taste would be better.
And those who will come under that tree
will receive the fruits of that tree.
But a fruit which is separated
will be lost after some time.
That is how one has to very collective.
Sahaja Yogi: How to develop
our discrimination, Mother?
Shri Mataji: Discrimination
comes through Hamsa Chakra, more.
And Hamsa is a very simple thing,
is to put some ghee in the nose,
is the physical thing.
On the emotional side, one
should not cry too much.
Or women specially have too much crying business.
I also sometimes feel like crying, but seldom.
So sometimes men must cry also.
Now spiritually, to develop discrimination
is by vibratory awareness.
When your vibrations are developed,
then you automatically discriminate.
You are such a big computer.
It has to work in its full way, and then
you’ll be amazed what a computer you are.
I’ll give you an example of Warren now.
There was a,
Pat’s husband Prole [David], who was
measuring My house for certain purpose,
while Warren was sleeping.
Poor David was working, Warren was sleeping.
And in his dream, he dreamt that he
had finished with the last measurement.
And in his half-sleep he got up
and he told him that this
house measures, how much?
Warren: Three thousand
nine hundred and sixteen square feet.
Shri Mataji: Three thousand nine
hundred and sixteen square feet.
And ‘exactly’ that’s what he
had written! David Prole.
Poor David had worked
so hard measuring everything!
He actually fell from his
chair, you see, he couldn’t sit!
Like today I told Guido
that I think I spent three
hundred and eighty pounds.
And he said, no it was three hundred.
I never calculated, nothing. I just said it.
And by calculation, it was 379,
according to him but I gave
him one pound more! So it was 380.
It’s a fact!
That’s how you become a computer.
All mathematics comes through your brain.
It’s so, it's so dynamic.
But first of all you have to have concentration,
concentration of your devotion.
Such a person achieves that.
There are so many blessings
waiting for all of you, to be manifested.
Just you have to concentrate
your efforts in devotion
and dedication.
May God Bless You.